Leo Isacson Papers TAM.306
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Leo Isacson Papers
1920-1996
1945-1949
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Isacson, Leo, 1910-1996
Bloom, Dale Isacson
TAM.306
5.17 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 4 oversize flat boxes.
Leo Isacson (1910-1996) was an attorney and politician from Bronx, NY. In a 1948 special election he was elected to the seat for New York's 24th District of the United States House of Representatives as the American Labor Party candidate. The victory shocked the political establishment and commentators. In that November's general election, the mainstream political parties worked in a coalition to unseat him. The collection chronicles Isacson's life, with particular emphasis the 1948 campaign and his subsequent service in Congress. Included are clippings, photographs, campaign materials, correspondence, and writings. There are four boxes of scrapbooks, comprised primarily of clippings, that document the campaign, Isacson's brief career in the House, and the analysis of Isacson's unexpected victory.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials donated by Dale Isacson Bloom in 1998. The accession numbers related to this gift are 1998.022, 1998.023, and NPA.2003.023.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series: Series 1. Papers; Series 2. Photographs and Nonprint Materials.
Historical/Biographical Note
Leo Isacson (1910-1996) was an attorney and politician from Bronx, NY. In a 1948 special election he was elected to the seat for New York's 24th District in the United States House of Representatives as the American Labor Party candidate. The victory shocked the political establishment and commentators. Isacson's tenure in the House coincided with the escalation of the Cold War, and while a member of the House of Representatives, the State Department denied him a passport to travel to France. In the general election in the November of that year, the mainstream political parties worked in a coalition to unseat him. Following his defeat, Isacson returned to his law practice, and later in life he taught political science at Nova University in Fort Lauderdale.
Scope and Content Note
The collection chronicles the life of attorney and politician Leo Isacson with particular emphasis on his 1948 campaign for the United States House of Representatives on the American Labor party ticket and subsequent service in Congress. Included are clippings, photographs, campaign materials, correspondence, and writings. There are four boxes of scrapbooks, comprised primarily of clippings. These document the campaign, Isacson's brief career in the House, and the analysis of Isacson's unexpected victory. Other subjects represented include the relationship between Isacson and the campaign of Progressive Party presidential candidate Henry Wallace, Congressman Vito Marcantonio, Isacson's views on the state of Israel, and a peace trip to the Soviet Union.
Legislators -- United States.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Isacson, Leo, 1910-1996; Bloom, Dale Isacson
- Papers
  - Political Scrapbooks (Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5)
- Photographs and Nonprint Materials
  - Democratic National Convention, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Demonstrations (Box 1)
  - Events, unspecified (Box 1)
  - Friends / Family (Box 1)
  - Isacson speaking (Box 1)
  - Landscapes (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (includes photos of campaigning) (Box 1)
  - Portraits of Leo Isacson (Box 1)
  - Strikes (Box 1)
  - Color Photo Album from Florida (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook - 1935-1945 - Photocopy (Box 1)
  - Photos from Scrapbook - 1935-1945 (Box 1)
  - Photos from Scrapbook - 1935-1945 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, other than photos (Box 1)
  - Postcards (Box 1)
  - Pass to 1968 Democratic National Convention - Chicago, illinois (Box 1)
  - Canada Lee [phonograph record], 1 access CD (Box 6)
  - Johannes Steel - recording for Isaacson campaign [sic.] [phonograph record], 1 Access CD (Box 6)
  - William S. Gailmor - English Record - Isaacson Campaitn [sic.] [phonograph record], 1 access CD (Box 6)
  - Oversize Materials (Box Shared Tamiment 142, Folder 9)